<?xml version="1.0"?>
<modsCollection xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3 http://www.loc.gov/standards/mods/v3/mods-3-2.xsd" xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
  <mods>
    <titleInfo>
      <title>Wnt signaling and the evolution of embryonic posterior development</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="local">journalArticle</genre>
    <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Martin</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Benjamin L</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Kimelman</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem type="host">
      <part>
        <detail type="volume">
          <number>19</number>
        </detail>
        <detail type="issue">
          <number>5</number>
        </detail>
        <extent unit="pages">
          <start>R215-9</start>
          <end>R215-9</end>
        </extent>
      </part>
      <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>Mar 10, 2009</dateIssued>
        <dateCaptured>2009-04-17 20:42:47</dateCaptured>
      </originInfo>
      <identifier type="issn">1879-0445</identifier>
      <titleInfo>
        <title>Current Biology: CB</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <titleInfo type="abbreviated">
        <title>Curr Biol</title>
      </titleInfo>
    </relatedItem>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.01.052</identifier>
    <location>
      <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19278640</url>
    </location>
    <abstract>During vertebrate embryogenesis, most of the mesodermal tissue posterior to the head forms from a progenitor population that continuously adds blocks of muscles (the somites) from the back end of the embryo. Recent work in less commonly studied arthropods--the flour beetle Tribolium and the common house spider--provides evidence suggesting that this posterior growth process might be evolutionarily conserved, with canonical Wnt signaling playing a key role in vertebrates and invertebrates. We discuss these findings as well as other evidence that suggests that the genetic network controlling posterior growth was already present in the last common ancestor of the Bilateria. We also highlight other interesting commonalities as well as differences between posterior growth in vertebrates and invertebrates, suggest future areas of research, and hypothesize that posterior growth may facilitate evolution of animal body plans.</abstract>
  </mods>
  <mods>
    <titleInfo>
      <title>Regulation of APC/C activity in oocytes by a Bub1-dependent spindle assembly checkpoint</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="local">journalArticle</genre>
    <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">McGuinness</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Barry E</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Anger</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Martin</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Kouznetsova</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Anna</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Gil-Bernabé</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ana M</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Helmhart</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Wolfgang</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Kudo</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Nobuaki R</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Wuensche</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Annelie</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Taylor</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Stephen</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Hoog</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Christer</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Novak</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Bela</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Nasmyth</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Kim</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem type="host">
      <part>
        <detail type="volume">
          <number>19</number>
        </detail>
        <detail type="issue">
          <number>5</number>
        </detail>
        <extent unit="pages">
          <start>369</start>
          <end>80</end>
        </extent>
      </part>
      <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>Mar 10, 2009</dateIssued>
        <dateCaptured>2009-04-17 20:43:21</dateCaptured>
      </originInfo>
      <identifier type="issn">1879-0445</identifier>
      <titleInfo>
        <title>Current Biology: CB</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <titleInfo type="abbreviated">
        <title>Curr Biol</title>
      </titleInfo>
    </relatedItem>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.01.064</identifier>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.01.064</identifier>
    <location>
      <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19249208</url>
    </location>
    <abstract>BACKGROUND: Missegregation of chromosomes during meiosis in human females causes aneuploidy, including trisomy 21, and is thought also to be the major cause of age-related infertility. Most errors are thought to occur at the first meiotic division. The high frequency of errors raises questions as to whether the surveillance mechanism known as the spindle assembly checkpoint (SAC) that controls the anaphase-promoting complex or cyclosome (APC/C) operates effectively in oocytes. Experimental approaches hitherto used to inactivate the SAC in oocytes suffer from a number of drawbacks. RESULTS: Bub1 protein was depleted specifically in oocytes with a Zp3-Cre transgene to delete exons 7 and 8 from a floxed BUB1(F) allele. Loss of Bub1 greatly accelerates resolution of chiasmata and extrusion of polar bodies. It also causes defective biorientation of bivalents, massive chromosome missegregation at meiosis I, and precocious loss of cohesion between sister centromeres. By using a quantitative assay for APC/C-mediated securin destruction, we show that the APC/C is activated in an exponential fashion, with activity peaking 12-13 hr after GVBD, and that this process is advanced by 5 hr in oocytes lacking Bub1. Importantly, premature chiasmata resolution does not occur in Bub1-deficient oocytes also lacking either the APC/C's Apc2 subunit or separase. Finally, we show that Bub1's kinase domain is not required to delay APC/C activation. CONCLUSIONS: We conclude that far from being absent or ineffective, the SAC largely determines the timing of APC/C and hence separase activation in oocytes, delaying it for about 5 hr.</abstract>
  </mods>
  <mods>
    <titleInfo>
      <title>Bcl-2 Proteins EGL-1 and CED-9 Do Not Regulate Mitochondrial Fission or Fusion in Caenorhabditis elegans</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="local">journalArticle</genre>
    <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Breckenridge</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">David G</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Kang</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Byung-Ho</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Xue</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Ding</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem type="host">
      <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>Mar 25, 2009</dateIssued>
        <dateCaptured>2009-04-17 20:53:12</dateCaptured>
      </originInfo>
      <identifier type="issn">1879-0445</identifier>
      <titleInfo>
        <title>Current Biology: CB</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <titleInfo type="abbreviated">
        <title>Curr Biol</title>
      </titleInfo>
    </relatedItem>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.03.022</identifier>
    <location>
      <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19327994</url>
    </location>
    <abstract>The Bcl-2 family proteins are critical apoptosis regulators that associate with mitochondria and control the activation of caspases. Recently, both mammalian and C. elegans Bcl-2 proteins have been implicated in controlling mitochondrial fusion and fission processes in both living and apoptotic cells. To better understand the potential roles of Bcl-2 family proteins in regulating mitochondrial dynamics, we carried out a detailed analysis of mitochondria in animals that either lose or have increased activity of egl-1 and ced-9, two Bcl-2 family genes that induce and inhibit apoptosis in C. elegans, respectively. Unexpectedly, we found that loss of egl-1 or ced-9, or overexpression of their gene products, had no apparent effect on mitochondrial connectivity or mitochondrial size. Moreover, loss of ced-9 did not affect the mitochondrial morphology observed in a drp-1 mutant, in which mitochondrial fusion occurs but mitochondrial fission is defective, or in a fzo-1 mutant, in which mitochondrial fission occurs but mitochondrial fusion is restricted, suggesting that ced-9 is not required for either the mitochondrial fission or fusion process in C. elegans. Taken together, our results argue against an evolutionarily conserved role for Bcl-2 proteins in regulating mitochondrial fission and fusion.</abstract>
  </mods>
  <mods>
    <titleInfo>
      <title>A hypervariable invertebrate allodeterminant</title>
    </titleInfo>
    <typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource>
    <genre authority="local">journalArticle</genre>
    <genre authority="marcgt">periodical</genre>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Nicotra</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Matthew L</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Powell</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Anahid E</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Rosengarten</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Rafael D</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Moreno</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Maria</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Grimwood</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Jane</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Lakkis</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Fadi G</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Dellaporta</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Stephen L</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <name type="personal">
      <namePart type="family">Buss</namePart>
      <namePart type="given">Leo W</namePart>
      <role>
        <roleTerm type="code" authority="marcrelator">aut</roleTerm>
      </role>
    </name>
    <relatedItem type="host">
      <part>
        <detail type="volume">
          <number>19</number>
        </detail>
        <detail type="issue">
          <number>7</number>
        </detail>
        <extent unit="pages">
          <start>583</start>
          <end>9</end>
        </extent>
      </part>
      <originInfo>
        <dateIssued>Apr 14, 2009</dateIssued>
        <dateCaptured>2009-04-17 20:46:00</dateCaptured>
      </originInfo>
      <identifier type="issn">1879-0445</identifier>
      <titleInfo>
        <title>Current Biology: CB</title>
      </titleInfo>
      <titleInfo type="abbreviated">
        <title>Curr Biol</title>
      </titleInfo>
    </relatedItem>
    <identifier type="doi">10.1016/j.cub.2009.02.040</identifier>
    <location>
      <url>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/19303297</url>
    </location>
    <abstract>Colonial marine invertebrates, such as sponges, corals, bryozoans, and ascidians, often live in densely populated communities where they encounter other members of their species as they grow over their substratum. Such encounters typically lead to a natural histocompatibility response in which colonies either fuse to become a single, chimeric colony or reject and aggressively compete for space. These allorecognition phenomena mediate intraspecific competition, support allotypic diversity, control the level at which selection acts, and resemble allogeneic interactions in pregnancy and transplantation. Despite the ubiquity of allorecognition in colonial phyla, however, its molecular basis has not been identified beyond what is currently known about histocompatibility in vertebrates and protochordates. We positionally cloned an allorecognition gene by using inbred strains of the cnidarian, Hydractinia symbiolongicarpus, which is a model system for the study of invertebrate allorecognition. The gene identified encodes a putative transmembrane receptor expressed in all tissues capable of allorecognition that is highly polymorphic and predicts allorecognition responses in laboratory and field-derived strains. This study reveals that a previously undescribed hypervariable molecule bearing three extracellular domains with greatest sequence similarity to the immunoglobulin superfamily is an allodeterminant in a lower metazoan.</abstract>
  </mods>
</modsCollection>